Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Mark Green papers
1954-1991, bulk 1954-1978
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Green, Mark
1.1 linear feet
The papers of San Francisco Beat era photographer, journalist, and poet Mark Green consist of correspondence, biographical information, photographs, Nanny Goat Hill Gallery exhibition announcements, printed materials, and exhibition files for "Rolling Renaissance" (1968) and "A Kind of Beatness: Photographs of a North Beach Era, 1950-1965" (1975) exhibitions that Green helped to organize. Photographs by Mark Green are of notable figures and places in the Beat movement, including Allen Ginsberg, Robert Rauschenberg, and Clyfford Still, as well as photographs by others of Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Mark Green, and Jack Kerouac among others.
Provenance
Mark Green donated his papers in 1974, 1976, 1979, and 1991.
Related Material
The Archives of American Art holds an oral history interview with Robert Emory Johnson by Paul Karlstrom on March 14, 1975 that details the history of the Rolling Renaissance exhibition organized in part by Mark Green.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection was digitized in its entirety in 2010 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Mark Green (1932-) moved to San Francisco and became active in the "Beat Movement" as a photographer, writer, and arts advocate. He helped organize two major group exhibitions of beat-era arts and also founded the Nanny Goat Hill Gallery in San Francisco.
Green was born in Cleveland Heights, Ohio in 1932, and attended the University of Miami, Florida from 1950-1952. After taking classes in journalism and philosophy, Green began a career in media and worked as a copy-boy, reporter, and correspondent at various newspapers throughout the United States until 1956.
In 1957, Green moved to San Francisco and worked as a bartender at the Co-Existence Bagel Shop, a local spot for Beat gatherings. It was during this time that Green became involved with the Beat Movement and the San Francisco Renaissance. Green became friends with "Beatnick" figures including Edward Silverstone Taylor and Patricia Marx who encouraged him to take up photography. Green's poems were published in Beatitude and The Real Bohemia.
A more prolific photographer than poet, Mark Green exhibited his photographs at Seven Arts Gallery, the Critic's Choice San Francisco Art Festival (1964), the Focus Gallery, and the "San Francisco Renaissance" at the Gotham Book Mart and Gallery (1975). He was active in organizing group exhibitions including the "Rolling Renaissance" (1968) and "A Kind of Beatness: Photographs of a North Beach Era, 1950-1965" (1975). Additionally, Green founded the Nanny Goat Hill Gallery (1972-1974) to give little-known artists an outlet to exhibit their works.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of San Francisco Beat photographer, journalist, and poet Mark Green consist of biographical information, correspondence, exhibition files, printed materials, scattered writings, and photographs. Photographs by Mark Green are of notable figures and places in the Beat movement, including Allen Ginsberg, Robert Rauschenberg, and Clyfford Still, as well as photographs by others of Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Mark Green, and Jack Kerouac among others.
One folder of correspondence includes letters from Jay DeFeo, Wallace and Shirley Berman, and Robert Emory Johnson. Exhibition files are found for two Beat exhibitions that Mark Green assisted in organizing: "Rolling Renaissance", 1968 and "A Kind of Beatness: Photographs of a North Beach Era, 1950-1965", 1975. Exhibition files contain correspondence, photographs of work exhibited and installation views, clippings, announcements and catalogs. Photographs are of Thomas Albright, Francis Ford Coppola, Allen Ginsberg, Leonard Hull, Robert Emory Johnson, Bob Kauffman, J. Oliver Mitchell, Francis Rigney, Jerome Stauber, and Edward Silverstone Taylor. Correspondents include include Thomas Albright, Wallace Berman, Bill Eisenlord, Alfred Frankensten, Allen Ginsberg, Helen Johnson of the Focus Gallery, Robert Emory Johnson, Chester Kessler, and Philip Whalen.
Mark Green's writings include a history of the Nanny Goat Hill Gallery, a statement about his photography, and various notes.
Printed materials consist of clippings, exhibition announcements for the San Francisco area and Nanny Goat Hill Gallery, and comic books.
The series of photographs is particularly rich due to Green's thoughtful and informative reflections written on the back of many of the photographs. The majority of the photographs identify the photographer, sitter, date, and place. Many times, Green included his own recollections of the particular sitter or photographer as well. In addition to photographs of Mark Green, there are photographs taken by Green and others of important Beat Movement figures. There are also photographs of beatnick "hot-spots" including the Co-Existence Bagel Shop, The Cellar, and The Place.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 6 series:
Series 1: Biographical Information, 1967-1970s (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1959-1976 (Box 1, 3; 1 folder)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1954-1975 (Box 1, 3; 13 folders)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, 1974-1978 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1959-1978 (Box 1-3; 8 folders)
Series 6: Photographs, 1950s-1970s (Box 2-3; 0.3 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Albright, Thomas; Coppola, Francis Ford, 1939-; Ferlinghetti, Lawrence; Hull, Leonard; Kauffman, Bob; Kerouac, Jack, 1922-1969; Mitchell, J. Oliver; Rauschenberg, Robert, 1925-2008 -- Photographs; Rigney, Francis J. (Francis Joseph), 1923-; Stauber, Jerome; Nanny Goat Hill Gallery (San Francisco, Calif.)
Subjects-Topical:
Beat generation; Bohemianism -- California -- San Francisco; Journalists -- California -- San Francisco; Photography -- California -- San Francisco; Photography -- Exhibitions -- California -- San Francisco; Photographers -- California -- San Francisco; Poets -- California -- San Francisco
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Writings
Names:
Berman, Shirley; Berman, Wallace, 1926-1976; DeFeo, Jay, 1929-; Eisenlord, William J., 1926-; Frankenstein, Alfred V. (Alfred Victor), 1906-1981; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-; Johnson, Robert E. (Robert Emory), 1932-; Kessler, Chester; Rennie, Helen J., 1906-1989; Taylor, Edward Silverstone; Whalen, Philip
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Information, 1967-1970s, Series 1:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  Biographical information includes Mark Green's resume, a xerox copy of a guest book of a Mark Green photo exhibition, and copies of exhibition announcements in which Green participated.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Mark Green, 1967 - circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1959-1976, Series 2:; (Box 1, 3; 1 folder)
  Correspondence is between Mark Green and others, including Wallace and Shirley Berman, Jay DeFeo, and Robert Emory Johnson. Correspondence is arranged by date.
  - General Correspondence, 1959-1976, (Oversized item housed in Box 3) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Correspondence, 1969, (Scanned with Box 1, Folder 2) (Box 3)
- Exhibition Files, 1954-1975, Series 3:; (Box 1, 3; 13 folders)
  This series consists primarily of materials relating to exhibitions that Mark Green helped to organize: "A Kind of Beatness" (1975) and "Rolling Renaissance" (1968). Also found is a catalog for "North Beach Memorabilia, the 40s to the 60s," (1968). Exhibition files include correspondence, clippings, catalogs, photographs, writings, announcements, and press releases. Photographs are of Thomas Albright, Francis Ford Coppola, Allen Ginsberg, Leonard Hull, Robert Emory Johnson, Bob Kauffman, J. Oliver Mitchell, Francis Rigney, Jerome Stauber, and Edward Silverstone Taylor. Correspondents include include Thomas Albright, Wallace Berman, Bill Eisenlord, Alfred Frankensten, Allen Ginsberg, Helen Johnson of the Focus Gallery, Robert Emory Johnson, Chester Kessler, and Philip Whalen.
  Exhibition Files are arranged into 3 subseries:
  Subseries 3.1: "A Kind of Beatness: Photographs of a North Beach Era, 1950-1965," 1954-1970s
  Subseries 3.2: "North Beach Memorabilia: the 40s to the 60s" [1968], circa 1970s
  Subseries 3.3: "Rolling Renaissance" [1968], 1967-1969
  - "A Kind of Beatness: Photographs of a North Beach Era, 1950-1965," 1954-1970s, Subseries 3.1:
    Writings, correspondence, and clippings relating to "A Kind of Beatness" exhibition which took place at the Focus Gallery in San Francisco, California in 1975. Also found are photographs which were included in the exhibition and photographs taken during the show.
    This sub-series has been scanned in its entirety.
    - Clippings, circa 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Bill Eisenlord
      Chester Kessler
      Wallace Berman
      Robert Emory Johnson
      Helen Johnston
      Philip Whalen
    - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Photographs by Mark Green, 1975, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 6)
      A. A. Gugel Jr.
      Edward Silverstone Taylor
      Unidentified Woman
      David Frankenstein
      Helen Johnson and Robert Emory Johnson
      Francis Ford Coppola
    - Photographs by Others, 1954-1959, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Bob Kaufman by Chester Kessler
      Paddy O'Sullivan by J. Oliver Mitchell
      Self portrait by J. Oliver Mitchell
      Jungle Jim, Leonard Hull, Jerome Stauber by unknown photographer
      Mark Green by Ella Henry
      Maitland "Sandy" Zane and Mark Green by Bill Paul
    - Writings and Notes, circa 1975, (See also Box 3 for oversized items) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Oversized Writings, circa 1975, (Oversized items from Box 1, F8) (Box 3)
  - "North Beach Memorabilia: the 40s to the 60s" [1968], circa 1970s, Subseries 3.2:
    This subseries consists of one exhibition catalog.
    - Exhibition Catalog, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Rolling Renaissance" [1968], 1967-1969, Subseries 3.3:
    This subseries includes writings, correspondence, exhibition announcements, and press releases from the "Rolling Renaissance" exhibition held thoughout San Francisco in 1968. Notable letters are written to and by Allen Ginsberg and Thomas Albright. Photographs taken during the exhibition include Allen Ginsberg, Thomas Albright, Robert Emoy Johnson, Dr. Reidar Wennesland, and Francis Rigney.
    - Correspondence, 1967, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Allen Ginsberg
      Thomas Albright
    - Exhibition Announcement, 1968, (Oversized item housed in Box 3) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Press Release, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Photographs by Mark Green, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Robert Emory Johnson and Dr. Reidar Wennesland
      John Hamilton
      Michael Bowen
      Dr. Francis Rigney
    - Photographs by Others, circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Writings and Notes, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Exhibition Announcement, 1968, (From Box 1, F10) (Box 3)
- Writings and Notes, 1974-1978, Series 4:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  Writings and notes by Mark Green include a history of the Nanny Goat Hill Gallery and statements about his photography. Also found are unidentified writings.
  - Drafts and Notes by Mark Green, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Writings by Mark Green, 1974-1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Unidentified Writings, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Printed Material, 1974-1978, Series 5:; (Box 1-3; 8 folders)
  Printed materials include clippings and newspapers, miscellaneous Beatnick publications, and comic books. Many clippings relate to the San Francisco Renaissance and the Beat Movement. Also found are materials from the Nanny Goat Hill Gallery including exhibition announcements, forms, and gallery schedules.
  The bulk of this series has been scanned. Only relevant clippings and the covers of comic books have been scanned.
  - City of San Francisco, 1975 August 10, (Oversized item housed in Box 3) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, 1959-1975, (partially scanned) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Comic Books, 1968-1969, (partially scanned) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Nanny Goat Hill Gallery, Exhibition Announcements, circa 1972-1974, (See also Box 3 for oversized items) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Nanny Goat Hill Gallery Forms, circa 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Nanny Goat Hill Gallery Schedules, circa 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Oracle, circa 1968, (See also Box 3 for oversized items) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Oversized City of San Francisco, 1975 August 10, (Removed from Box 1, F19) (Box 3 (sol))
  - Oversized Nanny Goat Hill Gallery, Exhibition Announcements, circa 1972-1974, (Removed from Box 2, F2) (Box 3 (sol))
  - Oversized The Oracle, circa 1968, (Removed from Box 2, F5) (Box 3 (sol))
- Photographs, 1950s-1970s, Series 6:; (Box 2-3; 0.3 linear feet)
  This series includes photographs of Mark Green, by Mark Green, and by other photographers. Photos are arranged by photographer and subsequently by date that Mark Green specified. Unidentified photographs do not have any identifying descriptions on the back.
  - Photos of Mark Green, 1959-1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    by Ella Henry Fitzgerald
    by Sally Green
    by Eric Mueller
    by Mark Green
    by Gerhard Nicholson
    by Beatrice Hablig
    by D. O'Neill
  - Photos by Mark Green, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Co-Existence Bagel Shop
    Self-Portrait
  - Photos by Mark Green, 1962-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Ed Taylor (6 photos)
    North Beach mime troop
    John Droeger
    Hubert Leslie
    Richard Brautigan
    Blair Stapp
    Irene Travener
    Lyndon B. Johnson (3 photos)
  - Photos by Mark Green, 1970-1974, (See also Box 3 for oversized items) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Loren Sears
    Henri Lenoir
    Edwina Albright
    David Meltzer and "Friends"
    Jackie Baks
    Bob Seider
    Gerhard Nicholson
    Marcia Gray
    Mark Green
    Sally Green
  - Photos by Mark Green, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Jay DeFeo
    Dick Wahlburg
    Helen Johnson
    Wally Hedrick
    Bruce Connor
    Diane di Prima
    Jackson Allen
    Dr. Reidar Wennesland
    Clyfford Still
    Edward Silverston Taylor
    Alfred Frankenstein
    Nata Piaskowski
    Judith Johns
    Henry Hopkins
    William Wolfenden
    Rolando Castellon
    Robert Rauschenberg
    Paul Karlstrom
    Bob Kaufman
    Gregory Corso
    Harold Norse
    Neeli Cherkovski
    Art Grant
    Mary Miles Ryan
    Ansel Wetterhahn
  - Photos by Mark Green, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 11)
    John McDowell
  - Photos by Others, 1957-1959, (See also Box 3 for oversized items) (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Michael McClure, Phillip Lamantica, John Wieners, David Meltzer by Gui de Angulo
    Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Brue Lippincott, Kenneth Rexroth by Ed Nyberg at The Cellar
    Gallery Six Collective Expressionism by unknown photographer
    North Beach, San Francisco by Leo Krikorian
    The Place, San Francisco by Leo Krikorian
    San Francisco Beanicks at St. Francis by Bob Campbell
    Irene Tavener by Bob Snyder
    Claudine Bodner, Thomas Albright, Fletcher Benton by Bob Snyder
    Eric Nord by Joseph Rosenthal
    Mike Nathan by Bill Eisenlord
    Jay DeFeo by Jerry Burchard
    Bob Snyder photograph
    Mark Green by Edward Silverstone Taylor
  - Photos by Others, 1960, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Poetry reading by Peter Breinig
    Jack Kerouac by J. Oliver Mitchell
    Jack Kerouac, William Morris, Philip Whalen by J. Oliver Mitchell
    Charles Dawkins by Edward Silverstone Taylor
    Patricia Marx by Edward Silverstone Taylor (2 photos)
  - Photos by Others, 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Mr and Mrs Bob Snyder, Thomas Albright by unknown photographer
    Kenneth Rexroth, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Mirium Patchen, Joanna McClure, Shig Murao, Jamie McClure, Gary Snyder, Peter Orlovsky by unknown photographer
    Jackie Baks, Wallace and Shirley Berman by Bill Paul
    Phil Linhares, Hayward King by Bill Eisenlord
    James Broughton, Ken Leroux by Bill Eisenlord
    Joan Brown by Beatrice Hablig
    Mark Green, Mr and Mrs Gerhard Nicholson by Bill Paul
  - Photos by Others, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Charles Dawkins by unknown photographer
    Knute Stiles by Moss Photography
    Nemi Frost, John Weiners by Bob Snyder
    David Meltzer by Bob Snyder
    John Ryan by Bob Snyder
    B. Bufano Studio by Joe Eareth
  - Unidentified Photographs, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Photos by Mark Green, 1970-1974, (Oversized items from Box 2, F9) (Box 3)
  - Photos by Others, 1957-1959, (Oversized items from Box 2, F12) (Box 3)